[music]
So, uh, welcome everyone to my talk,
Agents on Guard Rails, Deterministic
Safety for Database Operations. Uh,
we're going to do 75 slides and a song,
a musical gospel song that I prepared
for the occasion. It was cut from the
original presentation, but we're going
to have two minutes in the end. I'm
going to play it for you. So, uh, about
me, my name is Otim. I'm 40 years old
from, uh, near Tel Aviv. Until very
recently, I was CTO and co-founder of a
company called Origa. At Orga, we built
two, uh, pretty cool open-source
projects in the database space. One of
them is called Ant. Ant is an entity
framework for Go and Atlas is a
Terraform for databases a database
schema management tool. I'm going to
touch about uh touch on it a little bit
later today. Today as part of Honeybadge
labs I provide consulting for early
stage developerfacing startups. So let's
start. So uh coding agents have come a
long way in the past couple of years. We
went from tab completion to multifile
edits. Today we can get full pull
requests from a single prompt. I think
it's fair to say at this rate of change
and improvement that we are heading
towards a future of unattended software
engineering which means that in
inevitably we're going to need to trust
them with our production databases.
Uh, as someone who's been in I've
dedicated the past 5 years of my life to
protect production databases from
mistakes that can be made by developers
to nuke production. I find this kind of
scary and today I want to talk a little
bit uh uh about the ways in which agents
can mess up your production database and
see what we can do about them. We don't
want to give up all of these uh this
potential efficiency gains. So let's
start. When we talk about SQL, we
typically split into two kind of
distinct domains. One is DDL, data
definition language. How do we change
and define the schema of the database?
Things like drop a table or alter uh
create a index on a table. And the other
half is DML, select, update, delete.
Okay, the reading and writing of data.
So let's start by focusing on DDL. I'm
going to tell you a short story. Uh if
you remember this story, it's presented
as a song at the end of the talk. Uh so
here we have a developer and this
developer is requested by their product
manager. A very simple request. Hey, can
we please make the email column on the
users table unique because we don't want
duplicate values on this column and
messes up the reports and yeah, we don't
want to uh have any of that. So any
sensible developer would do today go to
cloud code uh let's prompt and ask to
make the the the changes unique. Now
this is a SQLJS and OJS from U framework
and cloud is able to find the right file
make the change and changing the data
model email column is now unique true.
Now our developer knows that the next
thing they need to do is to plan a
migration. Immigration is basically a
script that you're going to execute
moment before you deploy the next
version of the application to production
to bring the database schema to the
place where it needs to be. So we're not
going to do this ourselves. We're going
to ask Claude again to do this for us.
And we ask Claude to generate the
migration for us. So it knows how to do
the thing. It used the SQLiz CLI. It
creates the boiler plate. Then it
implements the placeholders. And at the
end of the process, we have the
migration. this is correctly
implemented. Okay, this is the right way
to do this in SQLJS.
Uh so the developer creates a pull
request goes through all the standard
hoops. So there's the PR CI is green,
the teams gives the thumbs up, it goes
through staging, everything is
by the book. Okay.
And now it's time to go live. And then
has to be an end. Then uh something
happens. We deploy and system blows up.
DB CPU goes to the roof. 100% error rate
on the critical endpoints in our backend
system, which is of course correlated
with 100% unsatisfied
management. Our CTO is kind of angry
right now. What the heck is going on?
Why did this happen? Okay, so in our
application, we're using a Postgress
database. Pretty popular. Most of you
are probably using it today in
production. And in Postgress, if you ask
the database to make an existing column
unique to implement that change, it
needs to uh acquire an access exclusive
lock on the users table, which means
that there are no reads or rights
allowed for the duration of the change.
So what happens is postquest to maintain
the integrity. If you remember from
acid, the I is the integrity. So we need
to verify the rule before applying it.
We stop the world. No arrays and rights.
We build the index from scratch. If this
is a large table, this can take a while.
It's a full table scan. And then we
reconstruct the data structure that can
maintain the uh uniqueness. This takes
disk. It takes resources. This can be a
time-consuming operation. Once
everything is done, the lock is
released. In the meantime,
any request to our server that wants to
do anything with the users table needs
to wait for the lock to be released. The
requests start piling up. Eventually, we
uh are out of connections. Our
connection pool is depleted and then all
requests coming into the server fail
even if they don't have anything to do
with the users's table. So, not a great
outcome. And as engineers, of course, we
want to ask, can this be prevented? So
turns out in Postgress there is a way to
do this safely. So we can create the
index concurrently and then we add the
constraint with the using index keyword
which can tells Postgress hey this index
this uh uh we know that this column is
unique using this index and you can just
now this turns into a metadata lock
which is very very fast and
unnoticeable.
I would have loved to know this before
deploying my change to production. Okay,
so we need some form of guardrails. The
agent here did the right thing, but it
still somehow managed to nuke the
database in production. Uh, good time to
introduce Atlas is something I worked on
with my co-founder at at Origa who built
this out. This is still uh uh going on.
Really, really great product. It's
called the Terraform for databases. So,
kind of a more modern DevOps approach to
to working with uh database schema. And
one of the cool features that Atlas has
is the migrate lint command which is
basically static code analysis for DDL
statements. So it will reconstruct the
current state of the database. It will
understand what the changes you want to
make and it will run them through a set
of analysis of analyzers 30 plus
analyzers database specific and it will
tell you stuff like this is a
destructive change. It's going to delete
data. This is going to lock the table
and you can also set your own uh
policies if you want to enforce stuff
specific to your use case.
In our case, if we had run the migrate
lint command against our specific
change, we would have gotten this adding
unique constraint on table users
acquires and access exclusive log bloing
blocking both reads and writes. I would
have loved to know this before uh
approving cla's changes. This would have
been great. So, we are in uh end of
2025. So, we don't just you know run
commands in the terminal anymore. So we
can wrap atlas with a cloud uh slash
command that basically tells us this is
the process from now going on how to
plan a schema change and then we can use
this in our workflow. So we do SL schema
make the emails unique. Now claude is
going to do its thing. It's going to
find the data model to update. It's
going to plan the migration and then
it's it will run the migrate lint
command. This is part of the prompt for
this tool uh that we have created. And
at the end of the process we get this.
Okay. So cloud basically stops and tells
us okay this is pretty valuable. This is
going to lock the table causing us a
problem. But as you know agents are not
100% reliable at using the tools that
you provide them. Developers might not
know about this slash command. So if you
really want something robust you're
going to connect this to a GitHub action
or to the CI system. So you're going to
basically have a a deterministic wall
that these type of changes cannot be
merged without any explicit approval.
The pull request is going to be read and
uh whatever work the the agent uh
generates or hallucinates is going to be
protected by some formal guardrails. So
key takeaways use some local tool to
inform agents of risk and use CI
guardrails to enforce safety. We talked
about DDL changing the database schema a
rare but risky operations more
day-to-day reading and writing from the
database. So let's consider databases
plus agents at runtime. Last November
anthropic released MCP
all about enhancing the models context
giving more information access to
information and access to tools. The
models can now interact with the
external world.
What better context to provide to the
model than the database itself. The
database contains the state, contains
the data.
Think about the possibilities, right?
Everything that we can do. So this
April, Google released MCP toolbox for
databases. Essentially the connective
tissue between agents and databases. And
they have built a ton of integrations.
This makes it practically free to create
an integration between your database and
your uh agent that you're working on. So
it's basically you brew install the
thing, you add this to your MCP toolbox
uh to your MCP servers JSON and then you
can do stuff like uh okay claude
tell me about this databases you we are
connected to. So it will use the list
the list tables tool and basically do
like a schema introspection to
understand. So this is like a CMS
blogging platform that we are connected
to. Now it will ask who are the top
authors in this uh system and it will
use the execute SQL tool to generate
this report. So who are so we have Bob
Bob is our top uh top contributor to
this uh blog post. So this is super cool
if you are just hacking locally you know
you are a trusted user it's cool that
you going to access production or access
the database directly and you get to you
know review all the MCP tool calls
before they are they're made. So it's
kind of maybe not ideal but but it can
work. But what if we are building an
agent for users? So something that users
are going to be uh uh using directly and
we still want to give this connection
between the agent and uh the database.
So allowing agents to query uh
production databases. I'm the second
person in a row to reference this
incident of uh uh Jason Lmin and the
deleted database. So it's a risky thing,
right? the the the if we lose the
database, our company is kind of gone or
at least in very serious trouble. So, we
want to be careful about doing that. So,
let's put this MCP server on Rails.
So, we're going to stop using the
execute SQL tool. No more direct access
to just, you know, generate a query and
we're going to replace it with
structured tools. So, MCP toolbox
supports this tools YAML file. you can
define the data source and then provide
it with a closed set of queries of tools
that it's going to expose as the uh
tools of the MCP server and these are
the only things that the agent is going
to be able to invoke against the
database. Each tool definition
provides the inputs. So what are the
knobs that the model can set and then
the query this is our edit post uh tool
and you will notice these dollar two
dollar three these are the placeholders
from the uh input tool. So these are ex
uh interpolated at uh runtime and this
enables us to do something. You're
acting uh on behalf of Bob top
contributor. Please set the title of his
latest piece uh to this and that. And
now uh Claude tries to use XSQL. It's
not available anymore. It figures out
who are the who is the top author, who's
this Bob, and it uses the available
tools uh to make the change that we
asked it for. Okay. And we can use uh
another prompt to ask for the result.
And we can see now that we were able to
uh change Bob's blog post to these
hacker uh caps uh notation.
So, you may have noticed something weird
I wrote in the prompt. You're acting on
behalf of Bob. This should kind of bring
on the the red uh alarm light in your
mind cuz you probably heard about SQL
injections, right? When we use uh add a
semicolon at the end of some input and
we use that to kind of uh change the way
a system is supposed to work to do
malicious stuff. Now we are dealing with
prompt injection. So we have different
prompts we can give the database the the
agent to kind of change its behavior to
act as on behalf of a different user.
And we can't let LLMs to decide their
own authentication what they are allowed
to do. Okay? It cannot be like an input
that the the the agent gets to set. Uh
it needs to be something that is done
externally. So MCP toolbox provides
authenticated parameters. And to uh
demonstrate this, I built a small demo
application where I'm logged in with
Google authentication. And I'm going to
try to do the same thing. I'm going to
uh try to edit Bob's uh post. So I want
to prevent this with these uh
authenticated parameters which work by
defining an O services. So we're telling
the MCP toolbox who is the identity
provider. Okay. So it can verify that
the person that's supposedly uh the
agent is acting on behalf of uh is the
right person and we can now create tools
that are autoop populated from the
authenticated user's email. Right? So
this is like a reference to a field in
the uh uh um in the JWT token that is uh
provided and then what we do is we kind
of add to the wear clause of this tool
uh something that verifies that the ID
of the user is the value that we got
from the identity provider. So basically
now if someone tries to act on behalf of
someone that is not them the query will
not work. It will return it will be like
a no op. Uh so just a bit of code is uh
we're going to initialize this set of
tools. We're going to take the whatever
the MCP server provides and wrap it with
this authentication uh uh token in
injection thing. Uh we create this
decorator in Python to make sure that we
always propagate the bearer token the
the API key or the the uh the identifier
that we get from the client into the
request context. And then we can uh
whenever we initialize the agent, we
make it such that whenever the tools are
called, we propagate the identity all
the way from the identity provider all
the way to the MCP toolbox that can
decide to reject the calls uh or sorry
to inject these values into the tool
calls. And then finally, what this looks
like is I'm going to sign in. I'm going
to update Bob's most recent post,
telling the the agent how to find it.
and it tells me it cannot be done
because you don't have permission. Okay.
Okay. Update my post. Uh find it via the
leaderboard and update it to Devcon
2025. And then bam, uh it works. So key
takeaways,
no execute SQL tool for production
agents. Uh instead provide them with
tools with pre-approved queries. Set the
guard rails here so you can control what
happens. Don't let agents set uh
sensitive inputs. instead set them
yourself via code. And we covered DDL
changing the database. We saw how we can
use Atlas or similar tools to do some
sort of deterministic validation of
schema changes that are proposed by the
agent. We saw DML and how we can kind of
set guard rails around that using the
tools provided to us with uh Google's
MCP uh toolbox. And with that, thank you
very much. [applause]
How are we on time?
>> Oh, yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Okay. Because we have a two-minute song
at the end.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh, so any questions?
>> What is your Oh, thank you. That's all
right.
>> All right. What is your stance on um use
like doing direct SQL but only in a
readonly state like one of the things
would be like deep analytics like
analysis type things do you do you worry
about those same types of things as well
>> so uh really depends on the setting and
what is the application that you're
building but for example this thing that
I showed with MCP toolbox in postquest
can be achieved by rowle security right
where you kind of inject the user ID you
can use database mechanisms I think the
the the authenticated parameter is cool
because it's supported across a very
wide range of databases and but if you
are like working towards a specific use
case and you can use database
permissions control they're usually a
lot of times not granular enough but if
that works in your specific database
sure
>> okay
>> I get your question um [clears throat]
it seems like you you have a very small
set of like allowed actions right saying
hey these possibly you had three as an
example but it's really limiting like
the expressivity of the agent is to be
able to work with like whatever
ecosystem you're plugging into in this
case Postgress like do you think that
that's going to scale like you're
expecting everybody to follow this
example and say hey three goes to 300
allowed actions and we're really just or
or is the the opposite side of that
where you just maybe your question was
similar which was is there not just like
a higher level action that we're just
saying hey please don't delete anything
like if If it includes a delete or a
drop, then this should not be permitted
at all. Something that's kind of like
>> So, so I think uh this is just one tool.
There's many ways to limit to set the
guardrails. I think the the important
takeaway is to be mindful about what you
let the agent do. So, MCP toolbox let
you compose like an hierarchy of tool
sets that's available in MCP. So you can
it can be actually a larger group of uh
of queries that you open up uh in cases
where you trust the user enough and you
have like a a a protection
mechanism on the database side such that
you know that you you're not leaking out
data that the the user is not supposed
to see then that's fine. But it's still
like within the same rails of of a realm
of we have guard rails. We have stuff
that's not just like we're prompting the
agent not to do what it's allowed. we
have some actual like deterministic
boundaries that are going to prevent
stuff from from happening. So definitely
this limits the expressivity of text to
SQL which is amazing for especially on
an analysis use case. Um but you know
I've seen a company that does they're
using TSO. It's like a a SQLite thing
where they create like a a separate
database per tenant and then you know
they connect to the specific tenant
database and then you know it's it's a
readonly use case. they they spin up a
like a fork of the database that you can
basically work against and then the the
blast radius is very limited. You cannot
access another user's data and you
cannot cause damage to your existing
data. So you know but that that's the
same guardrails thinking is just
different mechanisms of enforcing
>> [music]